Guide to the Martin Gardner Papers SC0647
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Game files, Series 1
  - Dudeney, 5 folder(s)
    - Dudeney Scrapbook, Vol I, 1972-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Photocopies of scrapbook, containing articles, 1895-~1908
    - Dudeney Scrapbook, Vol II, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Photocopies of scrapbook, containing articles, 1909-1915(?)
  - "e" & Catenary, 7 folder(s)
    - 1961, October, 1960-1999 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      'e', the exponential constant
      Mostly articles on 'e'
      O'Shea, Owen
    - Catenary and Tractrix Curve, 1959-1998 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      notes, articles
      Johansson, Torbjorn
    - Rational Fractions for 'e', 1961-1994 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      Hendrick, L.
      Feldman, John
      Clamage, Allan
      Lewis, Donald
      Patton, Robert
      Brown, George
      Heitz, Robert
      Lassen, Herbert
      Fuchs, Helmut
    - Mnemonics for 'e', 1957-1966 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Boucher, Claude
      Angrick, Warren
      Nottingham, R.
      Guiteris, Joseph
      Jarnagin, William
      Sanet, Morton
      Conklin, Edward
      Krall, Al
      Stand, M.
      Greene, John
      Swenson, Richard
      Widhoff, Gene
      Keast, F.
      Mage, David
      Gianino, Peter
      Kerslake, R.
      McKiggan, I.
      Smiley, Richard
    - Curious Problems & Formulas Involving e, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      Heiting, Ted
    - Hatcheck Problem (or Matching Cards), undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
      Unsigned, undated typescript "To Be Solved With Ease"
    - Decimal Expansion of e, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Eggs, 2 folder(s)
    - 1980, April, 1980-1997 (Box 50, Folder 10)
      Maxwell's Ovals
    - Letters on Egg & Bottle, 1980 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Eleusis II, 5 folder(s)
    - 1977, October, 1977-2001 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Varios other rules suggested.
    - Papers on Eleusis, 1980-1981 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Research on Eleusis, 1966-1982 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      Several of Robert Abbott's newsletters
      Jaworski, John
      Newman, J.Robert
      Dietterich, Thomas
    - Delphi (Kruskal), 1962-1977 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Copies of correspondance between Robert Abbott & Martin Kruskal
      Sackson, Sid
    - Pensari, 1985 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Induction games by Robert Katz
      Katz, Robert
  - Elevators
    - 1973, February, 1972-1973 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      Sherin, Richard
      Holmes, Robert
  - Ellipse
    - 1961, February, 1961-1999 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - ESP Machines - SRI (NASA), 5 folder(s)
    - 1975, October, 1975-1976 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Hoppe, Richard
      Diaconis, Persi
      Deutsch, Ronald
      Jones, Earle
    - Development of Techniques ..., 1974 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      "Development of Techniques to Enhance Man/Machine Comunication", by Russell Targ, Phyllis Cole, and aHarold Puthoff - Final Report for JPL, SRI Project 2613, Aug. 1974 (Technical Report)
    - Targ's ESP Machine, undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
      Model 100A ESP Teaching Machine, Instruction Manual, from Aquarius Electronics (Manual)
    - Letters From Parapsychologists (P&T, Tart, Cole, Schneidler), 1975-1976 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Elgin, Duane
      Cole, Phyllis
      Puthoff, Harold
      Targ, Russell
      Schmeidler, Gertrude
      Tart, Charles
    - ESP Testing Machines, 1975 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Reviews & ads of some machines
      "Testing for Extrasensory Perception With a Machine", by William Smith et.al., Air Force Cambridge Research Labs, Data Sciences Lab Project 4610, May, 1963 (Research Report)
      Scully, Tim (Aquarius Electronics)
      Honorton, Charles
  - Everything
    - 1976, May (Box 36, Folder 12)
      Note (What is There?) by (or from ) Smullyan
      Tompkins, Robert
  - Factorials, 3 folder(s)
    - 1967, August, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      article (incomplete)
    - R. E. Smith [1 of 2], 1967 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Original Robert Smith article on which the column was based, with correspondence.
      Smith, Robert
    - R. E. Smith [1 of 2], undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
      Computer printouts of factorials in patterns
  - Fallacies
    - 1958, January, 1889-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      photocopy: Current Literature, April, 1889 "The Ten Travellers"
      Mooney, John
      Allen, Ralph
  - Fibanacci Numbers
    - 1969, March, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Just the article.
  - Fingers, 3 folder(s)
    - 1968, September, 1968-2000 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Ring, Ken
    - Finger Multipication, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Counting & Number Bases, 1958-1968 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      Story: "How to Count on Your Fingers", by Fred Pohl
      Article: "Mathematics and the Folkways", by Martin Gardner, in Journel of Philosophy, 47/7, March 1950
      Mnemonic for Pi in base 8 (in Knuth letter)
      Pohl, Frederick
  - Flatland & Hilton
    - 1962, July, 1961-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      "Do We Have a Two-Dimensional View of Crime and Deviance?" by Karen Paldan
      Biography of C.H. Hinton, by T. Weston
      Robert, Gegory
      Calhamer, Allan
      Holmes, Larry
      Weston, Timothy
  - Flexagons, 4 folder(s)
    - 1956, December, 1956-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (Models in separate folder)
      History of flexagons
      models, comments, analysis
      flexapyramids
      Mott-Smith, Geoffrey
      Templeton, Hugh
      Little, John
      Polyakov, N
      George, Douglas
    - Bibliography, tearsheets of articles [1 of 2], 1956-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The Curious Family of Flexagons, Frank R. Bernhart
      Some Elements of Flexagon Theory, Frank R. Bernhart
      Interim Report on Hexa-Hexa Aberrations, Donald Comstock 24 Apr, 1979
    - Bibliography, tearsheets of articles [2 of 2], 1954-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Flexagon, Nauka i Zhizn (in Russian), 1970
      Tukey, John
    - Frank Bernhart's Work, 1969 - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Counting flexagons with Feynman diagrams
      On flexagon maps
      "Some Elements of the Mathematical Theory of Flexagons" (Part 1)
      "The Curious Flexagon Family"
      Mitchell, Phil
  - Fliess
    - 1966, July, 1966-1980 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Game Learning Machines, 6 folder(s)
    - 1962, March, 1961-1977 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Hexapawn
      Extendapawn
      Various analyses of games and machines
      Typescript of Hexapawn brochure, from W.R. Aul
    - Reader Reports on Hexapawn, Contests, etc., 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Other Simple Learning Devices, 1961-1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Computer "Family Tree" from Ballistic Research Laboratories Electronic Scientific Computer (BRLESC)
      GLIM Learning Machine (Game Learning Intellegent Machine), by Russell Yost
      NIMBLE (Nim Box Logic Engine) - Learns to play Nim
      Tit Tat To machine
      ACE - A Learning Machine
    - Reprints of Column & TV Use, etc., 1962-1967 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Including Mame Mamu Ka (Russian? magazine) - 1962
      Nature and Science Magazine(1966)
    - "Baby" Games (Minigames), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Checkers - 4x4 Analysis (MG & W. Grandjean)
      Go - 5x5 Analysis (MG & D. Nix)
      Chess - 5x5
      Pawns - 2x4 (2 matchboxes)
    - Checkers (5x5), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Analysis - MG, Knuth, Grandjean, Caswell
      Caswell, Robert L.
      Grandjean, W.B.
  - Game Strategies, 4 folder(s)
    - 1961, July (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Just the article (about Bridg-it and Halma, the latter a variation of Chinese Checkers)
    - Bridg-It and Twixt [1 of 2], 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      (Also called Gale.)
      Full analysis by Alfred Lehman: "A Solution to the Shannon Switching Game"
      Robot Gale players.
      --> Booklet in separate envelope, of Gale layouts with instructions for the Game of Gale, marked "Season's Greetings! The Hatchers", about 4x4 inches.
      Lehman, Alfred
      Gross, Oliver
    - Bridg-It and Twixt [2 of 2], 1961-1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      References to "Board Games folder".
      "Bridg-it on the 1401", by Gunter Wenzel
      Program (for Bridg-it) for HP-97, by Mordecai Schwartz
      Fergason, Thomas
      Wenzel, Guenter
      Reynolds, A.C.
    - Checker Problem, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      (related to Halma)
      22 move solutions, 20 move solutions.
      proof (by Vern Poythress) that 20 moves is minimum.
      Durling, Allan
      Poythrress, Vern
  - Game Theory
    - 1967, December, 1967-1971 (Box 19, Folder 19)
      Morra - board and instructions (Piet Hein game).
      Various papers by Rufas Isaacs
      Morgenstern, Oskar
      Isaacs, Rufus
  - Games, 5 folder(s)
    - 1973, January, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Sim, Chomp & Race Track
      Mostly article + Ian Stewart article (on Chomp)
    - Sim, 1972-1981 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Analyses: 5-Point Sim, 6-Point Sim, N-Point, Dual, Choice
      Dual game analyzed by Leslie Shader (mimeograph)
      Shader, Leslie
      Croach, Jesse
      Erdos, Paul
      Simmons, Gustavus
      McLeod, John
    - Race Track, 1971-1974 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      Sci. Am. Christmas card
      Demolition Derby & other variants (James Henle)
      Many variants
      Henle, James
      Nievergelt, Jurg
      Falconer, Tomas
    - Chomp [1 of 2], 1972-1973 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      "A Curious Nim-type Game", by David Gale (mimeograph) - original game discription
      "Game of Diisors", by Fred Schuh (typescript) translation by G.J.Westerink
      Thompson, Ken
      Winker, Steve
      Westerink, G.J.
      Lunon, Fred
    - Chomp [2 of 2], 1972-1986 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Partial analysis of 3xN Chomp, from F. Bernhart
  - Games (Jam, Hot, Etc.), 3 folder(s)
    - 1967, February (Box 18, Folder 8)
      just article.
    - Kayles (String Nim), 1964-1967 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      analysis by Henon
      Henon, Michel
      Spoerl, Charles
      Epstein, Richard
    - Squad Car Game, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Geometric Fallacies
    - 1971, April (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Golomb's Graceful Graphs, 5 folder(s)
    - 1972, March [1 of 2], 1972-1977 (Box 24, Folder 21)
      Many & various articles.
      "My views of the Problem", by Takashi Wakui, from Fascinating Puzzles Monthly No. 36, July, 1968 (photocopy)
      Lagarior, Jeff
    - Golomb's Graceful Graphs [2 of 2], 1965-1985 (Box 24, Folder 22)
      Hollingsworth, Lowell
      Reid, Robert
      Ashenfelter, Robert
      Robertson, Douglas
    - Results, etc, from Readers on Graceful Graphs, 1972-1994 (Box 24, Folder 23)
      Mixon, Bill
      Harries, Wolfgang
    - Disproof of Golomb Conjecture, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 24)
      "Large Graceful Subgraphs of the Complete Graph", by Gustavus Simmons (typescript)
      Van Rongen, J.B.
    - Recent Papers - Golomb, etc, 1982-1984 (Box 24, Folder 25)
      (Referenced in latest version of column in "Wheels, Life ...")
  - Graphs
    - 1964, April (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Application of Hamiltonian Lines to hydrocarbons (in Eckroth letter)
      Meally, Victor
      Eckroth, David
  - Gray Codes (& Chinese Rings), 4 folder(s)
    - 1972, August [1 of 2], 1972-1974 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      The Brain, puzzle from Mag-Nif, by Marvin Allison, Jr.
      "Cyclic Codes in Analog-to-Digital Encoders", by Chas. Cole (photocopy)
      Allison, Marvin
      Deutsch, E.
    - Gray Codes (& Chinese Rings) [2 of 2], 1972-1997 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Gray's patent (Pulse Code Communication), 1953
      Gray Codes & Dragon Curves (in George Darwin letter)
      Stibitz Patent (Binary Counter), 1943 (predates Gray?)
      Puzzles based on Gray codes (see Leslie Upton letter)
      "The Treasure of Grayham Binar" (also Leslie Upton letter)
      "Lucky Light", by Dave Lederman (magic trick)
      Darwin, George
      Stibitz, George
      Cipra, Barry
    - Chinese Rings, 1972-1998 (Box 25, Folder 14)
      Various commercial rings, Princeps Puzzle (electronic)
      Golomb, Michael
      Ray, David
      Rasmussen, Peter
    - Paths in N-Cubes, 1972-1985 (Box 25, Folder 15)
      Bradford, L.E.
      Winkler, Steve
      Vanderschel, David
  - Groups (Finite), 4 folder(s)
    - 1980, June (Box 51, Folder 1)
      No article (see next folder: 51/2)
      Lots of short articles on groups (& revies of books on groups.)
    - Sporatic Groups, 1968-1980 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      SA article.
      Golomb lists errors in column.
      Lots of MG notes, articles, etc.
      Grossman, Israel
      Lyons, Richard
      Gorenstein, Dan
      Griess, Robert
      McKay, John
    - Lie (Infinite) Groups, undated (Box 51, Folder 3)
      MG notes, a couple of book reviews
    - Galois, undated (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Articles on Galois, mostly by Tony Rothman.
  - Guy - On Primes
    - 1980, December, 1980-1981 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      Notes from Richard Guy. Relates to column & contains number curios NOT dealing with primes (& usable in Future Columns.)
      Mullin, Albert
  - Hakenbush
    - 1972, January, undated (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Halma, 9 folder(s)
    - 1971, October, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
      Just article & rules for Halma (& references)
    - Halma papers by Elithorn, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Many papers: preprints, typescripts, reprints, etc.
    - Halma Computer Programs, undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Transfer Problems, 1971-1983 (Box 24, Folder 9)
      Lots of solutions, by MG and others.
      Fujimura, Kobon
    - Halma Solitaire Problems, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 10)
      Mostly MG notes and solutions
    - 3x3, undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - 4x4, undated (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - 5x5 Square, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 13)
      Widdeer, Vera
      Gordon, Leonard
    - 6x6 Square, undated (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Hamilton's Icosian Game, 3 folder(s)
    - 1957, May (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Icosian Game
      Tower of Hanoi
      Hamiltonian Path
      (Polyominoes)
    - Tower of Hanoi [1 of 2], 1957-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      All you ever wanted to know about The Towers of Hanoi but were afraid to ask, by W.F. Lunnon
      Walsh, Timothy
      Katz, Sylvan
      Moeser, Robert
      Armstron, H.
      Paciulan, Kenneth
      Revennaugh, Vance
      Lunnon, Fred
    - Tower of Hanoi [2 of 2], 1957-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      (see model "The Great Pyramid", in box xxx)
      Ad, in French, of "Jeux Scientifiques" of Edouard Lucas
      The Towers of Hanoi" by Jay Kappraff and Gary Adamson
  - Harary's Generalized TTT
    - 1979, April, 1978-1979 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      "Achievement and Avoidance Games", by Frank Harary (typescript) -- written for MG for this column. (Talks about various games, and Ramsey Theory.)
      Austin, A.K.
  - Helix
    - 1963, June, 1960-1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Katsanis, Theodore
      Lind, Douglas
      Brown, Robert
  - Hex
    - 1957, July, 1957-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      History and discussion about Hex (MG, Nash, Gale)
      Con-Tac-Tix (a Piet Hein game)
      Nash, John
      Milnor, John
      Hayward, Ryan
      Van Ryswyck, Jack
      Browne, Cameron
  - Hexes & Stars, 7 folder(s)
    - 1974, July, 1972-1978 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      Photocopy of column, plus some partial cut-outs of the column & some corrections for next month.
    - Square Triangles, 1960-1988 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      "The Address Problem", by Michael Tennor (typescript)
      "Triangular-Square-Pentagonal Numbers", by R.J. Stroeker, Report 7701/M, Econometric Inst, Erasmus University
      Tennor, Michael
      Furry, W.H.
      Adler, Irving
      Jankovich, Gradimir
    - Hexes, 1974-1986 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Grinstead, Charles
    - Star Numbers, 1973-1974 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      Computer listing of some factorials, printed in "star" format
      Milwee, George
    - Triangle Stars, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      Wainwright, Robert
    - Square Stars, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      notes
    - The Pell Equation, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Hexiamonds, 5 folder(s)
    - 1964, December, 1958-1973 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      much general information, history, proofs, and solutions
      Lewis also deals with non-connected pieces, and ones connected at vertices. Draft of article.
      Williams, Merideth
      Povah, Maurice
      Struyk, Adrian
      Haselgrove, Jenifer
      Lewis, Charles
      Schaffer, Karl
    - New Material From Readers, 1964-1983 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - The 66 Octiamonds & Higher, 1964-1975 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      Penrose, Roger
      Escher, Mauritis C.
    - The Rhombi, 1964-1966 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Triplication Problems (and Twin, etc), 1964-1970 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Hyperbola, 2 folder(s)
    - 1977, September, 1961-1977 (Box 41, Folder 12)
      Thigs of Science: Curve Unit, No. 139 (Instructiions)
      Cibulskis, Walter
      Klein, Arthur
    - Hyperboloids, 1977 (Box 41, Folder 13)
      Information on McDonnell Planetarium
      Slides & photos of McDonnell shadows
      Sutherland, Ronald
  - I Ching, 4 folder(s)
    - 1974, January [1 of 2], 1970-1974 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      No article (but issue cover)
      Chen, S.T.
    - I Ching [2 of 2], 1974-1980 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      "I Ching Oracles", magic trick by Sam Dalal, in Swami, Sept. 1974
      "Pattern in the Arrangements of the Trigrams of the I Ching", by Nicholas Bolton & Nicol Macleod (typescript)
      Bolton, Nicholas
    - The Unsolved Problem of Hexagram Ordering, 1973-1986 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      "Defining Two Sequences of the Hexagrams in the I Ching by Their Linear Symbols", by Mou-Ta Chen (typescript)
      "The Riddle of the Number Sequence of the Chines I Ching - a Geomantic Solution", by Norbert Muller (thpescript)
      Miller, Aaron
    - N-Cube in Anthropology, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      "N-Cubes in Anthropological Theory", by Hans Hoffman, 1975 (typescript): paper includes section on I Ching as lattice.
      Hoffmann, Hans
  - Imaginary & Complex Numbers
    - 1979, August, 1965-1979 (Box 48, Folder 13)
      Notes and articles
  - Induction Paradoxes, 3 folder(s)
    - 1976, March, 1976-1986 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      Only snippet of article
      "Urning a Resolution of Hempel's Paradox", by Stuart Meyer (typescript)
      Meyer, Stuart
    - Solomonoff's Work, 1976 (Box 36, Folder 2)
      Articles by Solomonoff
      Solomonoff, Ray
    - Letters on the Pies, 1976 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      *Lots* of letters
      Berent, Paul
      Good, Robert
      Wittman, Donald
      Blyth, Colin
  - Inducton Games
    - 1959, June, 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Eleusis
      The Game of Eleusis
      Weinberg, Gerald
  - Joke Problems
    - 1963, April, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Weber, William
  - Joke Quickies
    - 1968, August (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Knights & "Cooks"
    - 1967, October (Box 19, Folder 12)
      Bruce, Robert
      Vasco, Charles
  - Knots, 2 folder(s)
    - 1961, September, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Huffman correspondence: lots of drawings
      Huffman, David
      Norman, Richard
    - 1983, September, 1983-1996 (Box 53, Folder 15)
      Penrose magic trick.
      Brown, Frederick (IGKT)
      Thompson, Don
      Rolfsen, Dale
      Trotter, Hale
  - Knotted Torus
    - 1972, December, 1958-1982 (Box 25, Folder 19)
      Proofs no 2 knots cancel.
      A torus, embedded in 3-space, can be knotted in only 2 ways
      Cutting a 2-hole solid torus to produce an outside knotted solid torus
      ... and more
      Turning an Arbitrary Two-Sided Surface Inside-Out
      "Untying a Knotted Torus", by John Stillwell (typescript)
      Stasheff, James
      Bing, R.H.
      Stillwell, John
  - Laffer, 4 folder(s)
    - 1981, December, 1981-1991 (Box 53, Folder 6)
      Dennett, Daniel
    - Letters on Laffer Col., 1981-1982 (Box 53, Folder 7)
      Rocourt, Georges
      Briland, Joseph
    - Phillips Curve, 1985 (Box 53, Folder 8)
      MG notes & some articles.
    - Laffer Curve II, 1981-1985 (Box 53, Folder 9)
      Mostly newspaper articles (1984, 1985) on Reagan economics & Laffer.
  - Latin Squares, 7 folder(s)
    - 1959, November, 1959-1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Graeco-Latin Square
      Design of Experiments (notes by MG)
      "Theoretical Studies on Orthogonal Latin Squares", by R. Aravamudhan (Orthogonal Array)
      Scott, Frank
      Betts, Donald
    - Order-10 Projective Plane (non-exixtance of), 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Arkins Work, 1972-1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Eulerian Magic Cube Problem of Order Ten
      Arkin, Joseph
    - Parker - Articles and Letters, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Orthogonal Latin Squares
    - Latin Cubes, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Taylor, Walter
      Peters, James
    - Bachet's Order-4 Card puzzle, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      analyses by Pugh and Goldenberg
      Pugh, A. Henry
      Goldenberg, Bernard
      Karfunkel
    - Diagonal Provisos and Arkins 10x10, 1967-1993 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Orghogonal Latin Square, Eulerian Square
      Black, Norton
      Most, Mel
  - Lattice of Integers, 2 folder(s)
    - 1965, May, 1962-1965 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      "Visibility of Primes", by Robert B. Ely, III (typescript)
      Ely, Robert
      Pryde, Geroge
    - Billiard Problem & G.C.D. Finder, 1961-1977 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Patent 2,978,816 (GED Finder), A. Zarrotsky
      Hayes, Brian
  - Left vs. Right
    - 1958, March (Box 3, Folder 5)
      About left- and right-handedness, mirror images and kindred matters
      Wiener, R.S.
      Silver, Helen
      Reis, Richard
  - Letters - Col. in general
    - Letters - Col. in general, 13 Apr 1989 - 13 Apr 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Schwenk, Allen
      Zimmermann, Mark
  - Lewis Carroll
    - 1960, March (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Only column; points to Doublets folder
  - Lightning Calculating Tricks, 2 folder(s)
    - 1967, May, 1946-1970 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Jaques, Richard
      De Grote, L.H.
      Hempel, Carl
    - Wallace Lee's Trick For Multipication "Magic No's", 1967-1972 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Copies of "Swami"
      Dividing by 7 tricks
      Lee, Wallace
  - Limits of Infinite Series
    - 1964, November (Box 13, Folder 17)
      article only (refers to separate folder)
  - Logic
    - 1959, February, 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Smith-Jones-Robinson problem (Dudeney's problem)
      Colored hats (Smullyan)
      Eddington problem "The Four Liars"
      "An Experiment in Symbolic Work on the IBM 704", by John Kemeny, 1956
      Biddy, Charles
      Youngdahl, C.A.
      Watson, R.
      Jonelis, John
      Smullyan, Raymond
      Hollo, Julius
      McMillan, Brockway
      Manheimer, Wallace
      Bookstan, John
      Fielding, James
      Osborn, Sidney
      Hooven, Frederick
      Matzger, Alan
  - M-Pire Problem (& Map Coloring)
    - 1980, February, 1978-1980 (Box 50, Folder 8)
      Taylor, Herbert
  - M.C. Escher, 7 folder(s)
    - 1966, April [1 of 2], 1964-1985 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      cloth "print" of Fishes & Birds (original??)
      Fomenko, A.J.
      Sakane, Itsuo
    - M.C. Escher [2 of 2], 1997-1998 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      various newprint articles
    - Correspondence - Corny Roosevelt, 1965-1981 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Cornelius Van S. Roosevelt
      (Photocopies of letters from Escher to Roosevelt)
      2 uncancelled Netherlands stamps designed by Escher
    - Correspondence - Escher, 1961-1981 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - About Escher [1 of 2], 1967-1999 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      various articles about Escher
      Schattschneider, Doris
      Graham, John
      Emmer, M.
    - About Escher [2 of 2], undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Newsprint articles about Escher
    - Photos, Prints, Postcards, 1971-1989 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      From an envelop, returning them from Doris Schattschneider to Martin Gardner.
      About 8 photos, 22 cards, 8 illus.
      Jacobs, Harold
  - MacMahan & 30 Cubes, 9 folder(s)
    - 1978, September [1 of 2], 1978-1979 (Box 45, Folder 9)
      "Some Notes on the 30 6-color Cubes,", by M.G. Harman (typescript)
      Harman, Michael